A Guide to the William Hewitt Phillips Papers, 1918-2008
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
William Hewitt Phillips Papers, 1918-2008
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2005-019
28.5 cu. ft. 57 boxes; 1 oversize folder
Papers of William Hewitt Phillips, NACA and NASA Langley Research Center aerospace engineer (and chief of Flight Dynamics and Control Division from 1970 to 1979), including lecture notes, reports and memoranda tracing the development of Phillips' theories while at Langley, spanning from his work on World War II-era aircraft to the early U.S. space program and beyond, as well as his interest in model aircraft.
Phillips, William H., (William Hewitt), 1918-2009
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The William Hewitt Phillips Papers were donated to Special Collections in 2005 and 2010.
Biographical Information
William Hewitt Phillips, known more familiarly as Hewitt Phillips, was born in Merseyside, England, in 1918, but moved with his parents at age two to the United States. He studied aeronautical engineering at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT), obtaining an S. B. degree in 1939 and an S.M. in 1940. During his childhood, he developed an interest in model aircraft, and he maintained an active interest in the hobby throughout his life.
In July 1940, Phillips commenced service with the National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics (NACA), where he was assigned to the Flight Research Division at Langley Research Center (Hampton, Virginia), specializing in the study of aircraft flying qualities and stability. Within this broader assignment, Phillips' task involved the improvement of World War II military aircraft flying qualities. Following the war, Phillips' research related to the development of jet-powered fighter airplanes, supersonic airplanes, stability augmentation and its effect on pilot control, automatic control, and gust alleviation. In 1947, Phillips married Viola Ohler, then head of Langley's editorial office. The couple had three children.
As the U. S. space program commenced, Phillips became chief of the Space Mechanics Division, supervising research in the areas of space rendezvous, navigation, and lunar landing and developing flight simulators for the Gemini and Apollo programs. To train astronauts for lunar landings, Phillips developed the Lunar Landing Facility. He later served as an analyst and consultant in the development of the space shuttle.
Phillips retired from NASA in February 1979 but continued in the position of distinguished research associate, performing original research on solar-powered aircraft, propellers, airfoil design and wind-tunnel studies of the use of canard surfaces for the space shuttle. He died in 2009.
Scope and Content
This collection contains the papers of William Hewitt Phillips, an aerospace engineer for the National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics (NACA) and National Air and Space Administration (NASA) at Langley Research Center and chief of the Flight Dynamics and Control Division from 1970 to 1979. The collection includes lecture notes, reports and memoranda tracing the development of Phillips' theories while at Langley and spans from his work on World War II-era aircraft to the early U.S. space program and beyond, as well as his longstanding and active interest in model aircraft design and testing. These papers include calculations of various numerical values in relation to various aircraft and spacecraft, as well as drawings and other illustrations. The collection also contains a set of Phillips' official reports, files devoted to lectures delivered by Phillips, and notes from courses and lectures presented by others. Major topics in this collection include aircraft stability and control; gust alleviation; wing theories; types of planes; shuttles; airfoils; gliders; simulation of space operations (particularly the Lunar Landing Research Facility), and model aircraft.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into two series, each representing a separate donation.
Series I, comprising the 2004 donation of papers, to a large extent retains the original order in which it was received, though some minor changes have been made for the sake of consistency. The majority of the collection, consisting of subject files, is arranged alphabetically by topic. Phillips' formal reports are arranged chronologically. The arrangement and file titles of a few folders have been changed to provide consistency to the alphabetical order.
The files were originally housed in four cabinets, later transferred to six boxes by the donor, and finally transferred to permanent boxes during archival processing. The contents of each original cabinet had been arranged in a generally alphabetical order, but there was no overall arrangement among the individual cabinets. Thus, the alphabetical order of the original Cabinet 1 comprises Boxes 1-5; of Cabinet 2, Boxes 5-11; of Cabinet 3, Boxes 11-22; and of Cabinet 4, Boxes 21-25. Phillips' formal NACA and NASA reports are arranged separately, in chronological order, and are found in Boxes 29-32.
Following Phillips' formal reports is a collection of materials relating to other writings and lectures by Phillips, previously in no particular order but here arranged chronologically; a set of files from lectures and courses presented by others, also originally found in no particular order, is now arranged by name of presenter and completes the collection.
Series II, the 2010 donation, contains the same types of materials found in Series I. These papers had no original arrangement but instead consisted mostly of loose papers together with a few individual folders and printed materials. The materials have been divided among five subseries:
Subseries I, Writings and Lectures. Included in this subseries are files relating to the output of Phillips' research, both in a professional capacity and as a model aircraft enthusiast. The files include not only drafts and published works, but background materials and correspondence. Arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
Subseries II, Subject Files. Arranged alphabetically, this subseries contains materials gathered by Phillips in the course of his research on various topics and his involvement in various professional- and hobby-related activities. Much of the material relates to Phillips' interest in model aircraft.
Subseries III, Correspondence Files. Though personal matters are sometimes discussed, the correspondence in these files relates largely to Phillips' work and his pursuits in model aircraft design, building, and testing. Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
Series IV. Photographs. Nearly all of the photos in this series are of Phillips individually or include him at various events.
Subseries V. Personal Life, Education, and Career. Included in this series are materials relating to Phillips' education at Belmont High School and the Massachusetts Institution of Technology. Also here are records and mementos from his NACA / NASA career, including his many awards. Documenting Phillips' personal life is a set of diaries that he maintained throughout his adult life.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Materials
The following items were removed from the collection and cataloged for the Rare Book Collection:
Maxim, Hiram S. Artificial and Natural Flight. New York: MacMillan, 1908.
Byers, Bruce K. Destination Moon: A History of the Lunar Orbiter Program (NASA Technical Memorandum TM X-3487). Washington DC: NASA, 1977.
Related Material
Phillips, W. Hewitt, Journey in Aeronautical Research: a Career at NASA Langley Research Center (Washington, D.C.: NASA History Office, 1998). TL540 P54 J687 1998 Large Spec
William Hewitt Phillips Autobiography, ca. 1995. Typescript draft titled "Research at Langley: a Technical Autobiography," later published as Journey in Aeronautical Research: a Career at NASA Langley Research Center. Finding aid available on the Virginia Heritage database. Ms2008-080.
Index Terms
Occupations:
Aerospace engineers; United States. National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics--Officials and employees; United States. National Aeronautics and Space Administration--Officials and employees
Subjects:
Archives of American Aerospace Exploration (AAAE); Science and Technology; United States. National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics; United States. National Aeronautics and Space Administration
Contents List
- Series I. 2004 Donation
  - Aileron Tabs and Damage Analysis, n.d. (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Airspeed, 1944, n.d. (Box-folder 1-2)
  - [Bell] X1 / XS-1, 1947, n.d. (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Bibliography/References, 1946-1953, n.d. (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Bomb Drop Proposal, 1942-1945, n.d. (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Canard, 1948 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Compressibility Theory References, [1945] (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Conference Notes, 1946-1950 (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Control Surface (Optimum Plan Form), 1942 (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Correlation Committee, 1946-1947, n.d. (Box-folder 1-10)
  - Corrosion, 1953 (Box-folder 1-11)
  - Delta Wing Theory, 1948, n.d. (Box-folder 1-12)
  - Dihedral, n.d. (Box-folder 1-13)
  - Douglas D558-2, X-3, C-54, 1945-1950, n.d. (Box-folder 1-14)
  - Drag Balance, n.d. (Box-folder 1-15)
  - External Stores Drag, n.d. (Box-folder 1-16)
  - Fabric Deflection, 1942-1944, n.d. (Box-folder 1-17)
  - Filters, Transfer Functions For, 1948, n.d. (Box-folder 1-18)
  - Flutter - Detached Tab or Spring Tab and Weight, 1944-1945, n.d. (Box-folder 1-19)
  - Flying Qualities, 1942-1946, n.d. (Box-folder 2-1)
  - Formulas, n.d. (Box-folder 2-2)
  - Frequency-Response Lateral, n.d. (Box-folder 2-3)
  - Fuel Slashing, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 2-4)
  - "G" Restrictor, n.d. (Box-folder 2-5)
  - Grumman, 1944-1950 (Box-folder 2-6)
  - Gust Recorder Flight Notes, 1947-1949, n.d. (Box-folder 2-7)
  - Gyro Errors and Effect on T.O., 1945-1949 (Box-folder 2-8)
  - Hinge Moments (Section & Finite Span), n.d. (Box-folder 2-9)
  - Instruments, 1950-1954, n.d. (Box-folder 2-10)
  - Jet Propulsion (Optimum Jet Angle), 1945, n.d. (Box-folder 2-11)
  - Landing Gears, n.d. (Box-folder 2-12)
  - Landing Theory, 1948-1951, n.d. (Box-folder 2-13)
  - Landings Glide Path Calc., 1949, n.d. (Box-folder 2-14)
  - Lateral Oscillations L-39 (Brisick's Work), n.d. (Box-folder 2-15)
  - Lenticular Satellite, 1963-1964, n.d. (Box-folder 2-16)
  - Light Airplane, 1946-1949, n.d. (Box-folder 3-1)
  - Lockheed P-38, P-80, 1952, n.d. (Box-folder 3-2)
  - Lockheed TV-2, 1953-1955 (Box-folder 3-3)
  - Martin XB-33 and Wind Tunnel Wall Effects, 1947-1950, n.d. (Box-folder 3-4)
  - McDonnell XP-67, F-88, F2H-2N, 1950 (Box-folder 3-5)
  - Moment of Inertia, Elev. (Prosphere), 1948-1953 (Box-folder 3-6)
  - North American XB-45, P-51P, XP-82, 1946-1950, n.d. (Box-folder 3-7)
  - Northrop, XP-56, B-35, X-4, 1949, n.d. (Box-folder 3-8)
  - Organization - NACA, 1949-1955 (Box-folder 3-9)
  - Oscillator, 1950, n.d. (Box-folder 3-10)
  - Propeller (Supersonic), n.d. (Box-folder 3-11)
  - Propellers in Yaw, 1942-1952, n.d. (Box-folder 3-12)
  - Quartic Charts, n.d. (Box-folder 3-13)
  - Reports, [1944-1950] (Box-folder 3-14)
  - Republic P-47, F-12, F84, 1943-1948 (Box-folder 3-15)
  - Rotary Servo Tab, 1948-1950 (Box-folder 3-16)
  - Section Operations, n.d. (Box-folder 3-17)
  - Servo Controls, 1942-1945, n.d. (Box-folder 3-18)
  - Sideslip in Rolls, P-63 and A-26, n.d. (Box-folder 3-19)
  - Sideslip Under Gravity, n.d. (Box-folder 3-20)
  - Spiral Stability, 1950 (Box-folder 4-1)
  - Spring Tab (for P-40), 1943-1949 (Box-folder 4-2)
  - Spring Tab Derivation, 1948, n.d. (Box-folder 4-3)
  - Geared Spring Tab, 1944-1948, n.d. (Box-folder 4-4)
  - Stability Derivatives, 1950, n.d. (Box-folder 4-5)
  - Stability, Directional, 1943, n.d. (Box-folder 4-6)
  - Stability, Directional, Ellipsoids, and Stability Derivatives, 1942, n.d. (Box-folder 4-7)
  - Stability, Directional - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box-folder 4-8)
  - Stability Equations, 1947, n.d. (Box-folder 4-9)
  - Stability Flutter of All Moveable Tail, 1951, n.d. (Box-folder 4-10)
  - Stability Lateral Oscillations, 1949, n.d. (Box-folder 4-11)
  - Stability - Longitudinal & Directional Oscillation, n.d. (Box-folder 4-12)
  - Stability - Longitudinal Divergence, 1941, n.d. (Box-folder 4-13)
  - Stability, Longitudinal - Wing Divergence Effect (Box-folder 4-14)
  - Stability Snaking, 1944-1950, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 4-15)
  - Stability - Snaking, Aileron (Final), 1944, n.d. (Box-folder 4-16)
  - Stalling Characteristics, 1948-1950, n.d. (Box-folder 5-1)
  - Supersonic Airfoil (Opt. Shape), 1946, n.d. (Box-folder 5-2)
  - Supersonic Flow, 1944, n.d. (Box-folder 5-3)
  - Sweptback Wings, 1948, n.d. (Box-folder 5-4)
  - Sweptback Wings (Dihedral), 1945-1948,n.d. (Box-folder 5-5)
  - Take Off in Cross Wind (Box-folder 5-6)
  - Turn, Pulling Into, 1942 (Box-folder 5-7)
  - 2-Control Airplane Stability, 1952, n.d. (Box-folder 5-8)
  - V-Tail, 1942, n.d. (Box-folder 5-9)
  - Vibrations in Recording Instruments, n.d. (Box-folder 5-10)
  - Vought XF60-1 Report (Unused parts), 1948-1950 (Box-folder 5-11)
  - Weighted Cable, 1942-1972, n.d. (Box-folder 5-12)
  - Wing Design - Swept Wing, Structural Consideration, 1945, n.d. (Box-folder 5-13)
  - Yaw Chair, n.d. (Box-folder 5-14)
  - Yaw Vane, 1942-1957, n.d. (Box-folder 5-15)
  - Acceleration Alleviation, 1949-1967, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 5-16)
  - Acceleration Restrictor (Box-folder 5-17)
  - Air Density Satellite, 1966 (Box-folder 5-18)
  - Apollo Conference, May 1965 (Box-folder 5-19)
  - Apollo, 1960-1962 (Box-folder 6-1)
  - Apollo Guidance, 1961-1966 (Box-folder 6-2)
  - Attitude Control Systems, 1959-1963, n.d. (Box-folder 6-3)
  - Bibliographies, 1952-1957 (Box-folder 6-4)
  - Biotechnology, Committee on, 1963 (Box-folder 6-5)
  - Boost System Friction, 1952-1954 (Box-folder 6-6)
  - Cable Gravitational Field, 1959 (Box-folder 6-7)
  - Calculus of Variations, 1957-1964, n.d. (Box-folder 6-8)
  - Circum-Lunar Mission, 1960 (Box-folder 6-9)
  - Committee Meeting Data, 1949-1961, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 6-10)
  - Conference on Operating, May 1964 (Box-folder 6-11)
  - Controls (Also Discontinuous), 1950-1959, n.d. (Box-folder 6-12)
  - Convair F-102, B-58, n.d. (Box-folder 6-13)
  - Directional Stability Report, n.d. (Box-folder 7-1)
  - Discontinuous Controls, 1960-1963, n.d. (Box-folder 7-2)
  - Discontinuous Controls, 1944-1967, [2 folders] (Box-folder 7-3)
  - Douglas DC-3, 1952 (Box-folder 7-4)
  - Dynamics - Large Displacement, 1951, n.d. (Box-folder 7-5)
  - Energy Storage Devices, n.d. (Box-folder 7-6)
  - EVA Extra-Vehicular Activity, Tether, OMPRA, 1965, n.d. (Box-folder 7-7)
  - Exams for Masters Degree, 1965, n.d. (Box-folder 7-8)
  - Feel Device and Overshoot in Pullups, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 7-9)
  - Fire Control - Aberdeen Conference, Feb 1952 (Box-folder 7-10)
  - Flight Programs,1971 (Box-folder 7-11)
  - Flutter, n.d. (Box-folder 7-12)
  - Fly-by of Planet, 1966 (Box-folder 7-13)
  - Front Fin for Offsetting Cross Wind, n.d. (Box-folder 7-14)
  - G Restrictor, 1953-1958, n.d. (Box-folder 7-15)
  - Gravity Gradient Dynamic Model, 1964, n.d. (Box-folder 7-16)
  - Gust Alleviation by Hirsch, 1967-1994, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 8-1)
  - Gust Alleviation (Weiss), 1951-1955, n.d. (Box-folder 8-2)
  - Gyro Lecture and Papers, n.d. (Box-folder 8-3)
  - Handling Qualities, 1951-1957, n.d. (Box-folder 8-4)
  - Handling Qualities, English Trip, 1948-1960, n.d. (Box-folder 8-5)
  - Height Bounced from Seats (Box-folder 8-6)
  - Helicopter, 1963 (Box-folder 8-7)
  - Hirsch Correspondence, 1980-1982, n.d. (Box-folder 8-8)
  - Hirsch Workshop, 1981, n.d. (Box-folder 8-9)
  - Hodograph Solutions, 1962, n.d. (Box-folder 8-10)
  - Human Pilot, Booster Control, 1956-1972, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 8-11)
  - Human Response Analysis, 1954-1972, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 9-1)
  - Ideas, 1953-1971 (Box-folder 9-2)
  - IFAC Talk on Gust Alleviations, 1971-1972, n.d. (Box-folder 9-3)
  - Inspection, 1956, n.d. (Box-folder 9-4)
  - Job Summaries for Annual Report and Status Report, 1958 (Box-folder 9-5)
  - Kalman Filter Theory, 1964 (Box-folder 9-6)
  - Lateral Equation, Time Vector Method, 1951-1954 (Box-folder 9-7)
  - Light Airplanes, T19, 1950, n.d. (Box-folder 9-8)
  - Light Planes, Longitudinal Stability, 1956-1982, n.d. (Box-folder 9-9)
  - Lunar Landing Research Facility (LLRF), 1963-1967 (Box-folder 9-10)
  - Magnetic Torque Analysis, 1960, n.d. (Box-folder 9-11)
  - [McDonnell] F4-C Investigations, 1967 (Box-folder 9-12)
  - Memorandums, 1948-1968 (Box-folder 9-13)
  - Midcourse Guidance, 1963-1965 (Box-folder 9-14)
  - Moon Surface, 1966, n.d. (Box-folder 9-15)
  - Northrop X-4, n.d. (Box-folder 9-16)
  - Parachute Reentry, 1958-1960, n.d. (Box-folder 9-17)
  - Power Controls, 1954-1955 (Box-folder 9-18)
  - Programs for Flight Research, 1959 (Box-folder 9-19)
  - Programs for Space Flight Research (Proposed), 1959-1961 (Box-folder 9-20)
  - Propulsive Efficiency (Tail Turbofans), n.d. (Box-folder 9-21)
  - Republic F-105, 1962 (Box-folder 9-22)
  - Roll Requirements, 1956, n.d. (Box-folder 9-23)
  - Rolling Aircraft Transient Resp. (Bomb with 1 Fin), 1951-1952 (Box-folder 9-24)
  - Rolling Airplane, 1951 (Box-folder 9-25)
  - Rolling Airplane (Bomb with 1 Fin, Rotating Space Vehicle), 1952-1954, n.d. (Box-folder 9-26)
  - Rolling Body, Gyro Stabilized Including Satellite, 1960-1968, n.d. (Box-folder 10-1)
  - Rolling Divergence - Methods of Reducing, 1955-1957, n.d. (Box-folder 10-2)
  - Sampled-Data System, 1957, n.d. (Box-folder 10-3)
  - Servo-Vane Control, 1948-1951 (Box-folder 10-4)
  - Simulation, n.d. (Box-folder 10-5)
  - Spinning Theory G. W. Braun, 1957-1972, n.d. (Box-folder 10-6)
  - Spiral Stability Device, 1953-1961, n.d. (Box-folder 10-7)
  - STOL Airplane, 1957, n.d. (Box-folder 10-8)
  - Systems Dynamics Test Vehicle, 1955-1959 (Box-folder 10-9)
  - Thrust Programming (Lateral), 1959-1960 (Box-folder 10-10)
  - Tops-Gebelein Analysis, n.d. (Box-folder 10-11)
  - Trailing Bomb, 1948-1963, n.d. (Box-folder 10-12)
  - Turbulence, 1955-1956, n.d. (Box-folder 10-13)
  - UN Conference on Peaceful Uses of Outer Space, 1960 (Box-folder 10-14)
  - University of VA Thesis Copies, 1970-1978 (Box-folder 10-15)
  - Unsteady Lift Report, 1952-1953, n.d. (Box-folder 10-16)
  - Variable Frequency Systems, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 10-17)
  - Vibrations of System with Spring Viscous Damping, 1962, n.d. (Box-folder 10-18)
  - VIMS Justification, 1970, n.d. (Box-folder 10-19)
  - Washout and Tracking Studies, 1969-1971 (Box-folder 10-20)
  - Water Rocket Theory, 1959-1988, n.d. (Box-folder 10-21)
  - Weathervane Damping, 1953, n.d. (Box-folder 11-1)
  - Work Programs, 1954-1957, n.d. (Box-folder 11-2)
  - Accident Report DC-10 (American Airlines Flight 191, Chicago), 1979 (Box-folder 11-3)
  - Acomotan Program, 1971, n.d. (Box-folder 11-4)
  - ACT Program, 1973-1979 (Box-folder 11-5)
  - ACT Program, TIFS Study for, 1976, n.d. (Box-folder 11-6)
  - Adaptive Control System Lecture, n.d. (Box-folder 11-7)
  - Aerodynamics, n.d. (Box-folder 11-8)
  - AIAA Committees, 1964 (Box-folder 11-9)
  - Air Traffic Control and RNAV, 1971-1977 (Box-folder 11-10)
  - Airfoil Theory, 1951-1978, n.d. (Box-folder 11-11)
  - Apollo Refs (Langley Work), 1991 (Box-folder 11-12)
  - Atmospheric Electricity, 1973-1978, n.d. (Box-folder 11-13)
  - Attitude Control, 1963-1970, n.d. (Box-folder 11-14)
  - Automatic Control, Performance Improvement Through, 1969-1970, n.d. (Box-folder 11-15)
  - Autopilot, 1976 (Box-folder 11-16)
  - Autopilot - Doug Garner's Electro-Fluidic, 1980-1993 (Box-folder 11-17)
  - BAC1-11 (Braniff Flight 250, Falls City, Nebraska), 1966-1972 (Box-folder 11-18)
  - Bibliographies, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 11-19)
  - Boundary Layer Oscillations, 1944-1967, n.d. (Box-folder 12-1)
  - Canard A/C, n.d. (Box-folder 12-2)
  - Career in Aeronautical Research, n.d. (Box-folder 12-3)
  - Catastrophe Theory (Bibliography), 1977 (Box-folder 12-4)
  - CCV (Control Configured Vehicle), 1971 (Box-folder 12-5)
  - CCV Comments, 1970, n.d. (Box-folder 12-6)
  - Coast Distance Calculations, 1977, n.d. (Box-folder 12-7)
  - Complimentary Filters, 1977-1978, n.d. (Box-folder 12-8)
  - Conference on Control Theory (Ames), 1964 (Box-folder 12-9)
  - Control Theory (Bridging the Gap), 1964-1972, n.d. (Box-folder 12-10)
  - Decoupled Control (Morse), 1971 (Box-folder 12-11)
  - Decoupled Control by Pre-Filtering Analysis, 1967-1970, n.d. (Box-folder 12-12)
  - Decoupling (Sundowner Problem), 1976-1977, n.d. (Box-folder 12-13)
  - Decoupling Analysis, 1968-1975, n.d. (Box-folder 12-14)
  - Decoupling Filters, 1968, n.d. (Box-folder 12-15)
  - Differential Maneuvering Simulator (DMS), 1967-1969, n.d. (Box-folder 13-1)
  - [Differential Maneuvering Simulator] TES-Tactical Effectiveness Simulator, n.d. (Box-folder 13-2)
  - Differential Synthesis by Ray Montgomery, 1968 (Box-folder 13-3)
  - Digital Computer for Glider DCGI, 1972, n.d. (Box-folder 13-4)
  - Display Research, 1975 (Box-folder 13-5)
  - Drag-Effect of Compliant Skin, 1966-1968 (Box-folder 13-6)
  - Dyna Soar (List of Reports), n.d. (Box-folder 13-7)
  - Facility, Flight Control Research, 1964-1977, n.d. (Box-folder 13-8)
  - Gas Turbine, n.d. (Box-folder 13-9)
  - Flapping Wings, 1969-1976, [2 folders] (Box-folder 13-10)
  - Flight Controls - McGraw-Hill Encyclopedia, 1979-1980, n.d. (Box-folder 13-11)
  - Free Body Dynamics Facility, 1961-1965 (Box-folder 13-12)
  - Glider Conference, 1975-1980 (Box-folder 13-13)
  - Glider Correspondence, 1971-1998 (Box-folder 13-14)
  - Gliders [2 folders], 1945-1978, n.d. (Box-folder 13-15)
  - Gliders, 1973-1979, n.d. (Box-folder 14-1)
  - Gliders - AIAA/MIT/SSA Second International Symposium on the Technology and Science of Motorless Flight (MIT), 1974 (Box-folder 14-2)
  - Gliders - Technical Soaring Article, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 14-3)
  - Gliders - Theory, 1970-1971, n.d. (Box-folder 14-4)
  - [Gliders] 3rd International Symposium on Motorless Flight, 1976-1978 (Box-folder 14-5)
  - Guns, n.d. (Box-folder 14-6)
  - Gust Alleviation - Eric Stewart, 1989 (Box-folder 14-7)
  - Gust Alleviation (Observers, Alt. Determination), 1973-1974, n.d. (Box-folder 14-8)
  - Gust Alleviation (with Autopilot) by Haines, 1967-1968, n.d. (Box-folder 14-9)
  - Gust Alleviation System, C-45, n.d. (Box-folder 14-10)
  - Gust Alleviation, C-45 - Time Response with Various Parameters and Pitch Damper, n.d. (Box-folder 14-11)
  - Gust Alleviation Theory with Pitch Damper and Speed Variations, 1970-1974, n.d. (Box-folder 14-12)
  - Gust Alleviator - Cessna, 1973-1979 (Box-folder 14-13)
  - Spanwise Averaging and Rolling Movement Reports, 1957, n.d. (Box-folder 15-1)
  - Vane Controlled Alleviator, Spanwise Gust Variation, 1969, n.d. (Box-folder 15-2)
  - Gust Calculations (C-45), 1970-1971 (Box-folder 15-3)
  - GWU [George Washington University] Foundations of Response Research Conference, 1986 (Box-folder 15-4)
  - GWU [George Washington University] - Figs. for Talk, [1986] (Box-folder 15-5)
  - Handling Qualities, 1954-1988, n.d., [3 folders] (Box-folder 15-6)
  - Hang Glider (Box-folder 15-7)
  - Hang Gliders, 1968-1978, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 16-1)
  - Hang Gliders Lateral Equations, 1974, n.d. (Box-folder 16-2)
  - Helicopter with Sling Load, 1973, n.d. (Box-folder 16-3)
  - Helicopters, 1976, n.d. (Box-folder 16-4)
  - Human Pilot - Foudriat and Wells, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 16-5)
  - Hydrofoil Boat, 1972-1975 (Box-folder 16-6)
  - Hydrofoil Derivation, 1971-1972, n.d. (Box-folder 16-7)
  - Identification, 1996, n.d. (Box-folder 16-8)
  - Inertia of Cone of Elliptic Section, 1975, n.d. (Box-folder 16-9)
  - Inspection, 1959 (Box-folder 16-10)
  - Kalman Filter to Measure Xg, 1974-1975, n.d. (Box-folder 16-11)